<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jacob Calvert</title>
    <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jacob Calvert</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:05:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jscalvert.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Random Markov chains have simple stationary distributions</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/asymptotic-uniformity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:05:05 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/asymptotic-uniformity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The stationary distribution of a continuous-time Markov chain is generally a complicated function of its transition rates. However, if the rates are i.i.d. random variables whose common distribution satisfies certain tail conditions, then the stationary distribution is essentially a simple function of the exit rates out of each state.  This is the main result of a new preprint with Frank den Hollander and Dana Randall, which generalizes and makes a precise prediction by Chvykov et al. (2021) and settles a question raised by Bordenave, Caputo and Chafaï (2012) under certain assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programming hierarchical self-organization</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/programming-hierarchical-self-organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 18:59:16 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/programming-hierarchical-self-organization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new preprint with Shunhao Oh and Dana Randall explains how to program simple computational &amp;ldquo;particles&amp;rdquo; of different types to self-organize into corresponding spatial regions that have a given hierarchical structure. The size, shape, and hierarchy of the regions are determined by the particles&amp;rsquo; densities and affinities for particles of different types. Proving that the algorithm works requires new techniques for analyzing the Gibbs distributions of fixed-magnetization models from equilibrium statistical mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New preprint on rattling theory</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/rattling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/rattling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dana Randall and I generalize and prove the main claims of an emerging physical theory of nonequilibrium self-organization, called rattling theory, by interpreting its main claims in terms of Markov processes. The result is a principle that relates a local aspect of the dynamics to the global steady state. We apply it to random walks on random graphs, spin-glass dynamics, and models of ant colonies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic clinical risk scores can cheat the AUC</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/auc-cheating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 11:45:26 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/auc-cheating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Clinical risk scores can cheat the AUC when the time that an adverse event occurs in a positive-class stay tends to exceed the duration of a negative-class stay. Risk scores should be compared to uniformly random scores that match their timing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper on critical numerosity</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/critical-numerosity-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 09:21:46 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/critical-numerosity-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My latest &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01919&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; introduces the concept of critical numerosity: A number of individuals above and below which the behavior of a collective qualitatively differs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dichotomy in models of collective motion</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/markov-chain-dichotomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 13:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/markov-chain-dichotomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post explains how the Markov chain dichotomy of transience and recurrence implies dichotomous behavior for certain models of collective motion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A third rigorous result about DLA</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/discrepancy-in-dla-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/discrepancy-in-dla-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post highlights recent work which constitutes only the third rigorous result about planar diffusion-limited aggregation (DLA), a paradigmatic model of random, dendritic growth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A conjecture about harmonic measure</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/a-conjecture-about-harmonic-measure/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 12:32:46 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/a-conjecture-about-harmonic-measure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given finite $A \subset \mathbb{Z}^2$, the harmonic measure of $x \in A$ is the probability that a simple random walk &amp;ldquo;from infinity&amp;rdquo; first visits $A$ at $x$. If $A$ has $n$ elements, what is the smallest positive harmonic measure that you can get?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerosity-driven phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/quorum-transitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 13:46:26 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jscalvert.github.io/posts/quorum-transitions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post discusses the intersection of some of my recent and forthcoming work in probability theory with studies of programmable matter and ant colonies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
