<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistical Physics on Jacob Calvert</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/statistical-physics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistical Physics on Jacob Calvert</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:05:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/statistical-physics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Random Markov chains have simple stationary distributions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/asymptotic-uniformity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:05:05 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/asymptotic-uniformity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The stationary distribution of a continuous-time Markov chain is generally a complicated function of its transition rates. However, if the rates are i.i.d. random variables whose common distribution satisfies certain tail conditions, then the stationary distribution is essentially a simple function of the exit rates out of each state.  This is the main result of a new preprint with Frank den Hollander and Dana Randall, which generalizes and makes a precise prediction by Chvykov et al. (2021) and settles a question raised by Bordenave, Caputo and Chafaï (2012) under certain assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programming hierarchical self-organization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/programming-hierarchical-self-organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 18:59:16 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/programming-hierarchical-self-organization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new preprint with Shunhao Oh and Dana Randall explains how to program simple computational &amp;ldquo;particles&amp;rdquo; of different types to self-organize into corresponding spatial regions that have a given hierarchical structure. The size, shape, and hierarchy of the regions are determined by the particles&amp;rsquo; densities and affinities for particles of different types. Proving that the algorithm works requires new techniques for analyzing the Gibbs distributions of fixed-magnetization models from equilibrium statistical mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New preprint on rattling theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/rattling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/rattling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dana Randall and I generalize and prove the main claims of an emerging physical theory of nonequilibrium self-organization, called rattling theory, by interpreting its main claims in terms of Markov processes. The result is a principle that relates a local aspect of the dynamics to the global steady state. We apply it to random walks on random graphs, spin-glass dynamics, and models of ant colonies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
